נח Nun Chet 58 and we start a new פרק perek קדשי
קדשים. Kodshei Kodashim. So now that we have laid out
all of the different קרבנות korbanot from the previous פרק perek and
exactly where they would be done, this is actually by the way
I think how most of us wish like a normal מסכת masechet
would start. One פרק, perek, here are the basic rules. Okay, you
know, this is this, this is this, this is this. Now let's
talk about what happens when things deviate from the rule. Okay, so
we had to wait till the fifth פרק perek to get the
opening פרק. perek. Okay, and now the next פרק perek is you
know where everything is supposed to be slaughtered, what happens and you
know where the blood is supposed to be put. Let's talk about
what happens if things deviate. So let's begin with this now with
נח. Nun Chet. קדשי קדשים שחיטתן ששחטן בראש המזבח. Kodshei kodashim shechitatan
sheshachtan berosh hamizbeach. So we know the holy of holies are slaughtered
in the north. What if they're slaughtered actually on the top of
the altar itself, not in the north of the altar? So I
have to tell you, I was once remembered I was at I
was like must have been twelve years old or something. I was
playing, you know, a miniature golf and they had this thing you
know we're going to now everybody's going to try to shoot the
ball whatever like in the whole court you know the one who
gets it closest to the hole or whatever gets I don't know
a free game or something. So I shot it and I got
a hole in one. So I didn't get the free game
because I didn't get to you have to get closest to the
hole. So anyway,
so okay, so if you're supposed to שחט shecht it to the
north of the altar, what if you actually שחט shecht it on
the top of the altar itself? Now what you could ask is
a question about does the top of the altar have the same
sanctity as the floor? Remember the כהנים Kohanim have to stand on
the floor whatever but presumably there the answer is like yes, like
it's all connected to the floor, it's considered like an extension of
the ground and so on presumably, you know, the כהנים Kohanim certainly
do the עבודה avodah when they're standing on the altar so you
know any sense that they have to be standing directly on the
floor so it's presumably there's no question whether it's considered like the
floor you know in terms of where the שחיטה shechitah is. So
what should the issue be? Well why not you figure out draw
a line and are you in the north side of the מזבח
mizbeach or not the north but it's supposed to be the north
of the altar, not the north of the Temple. So what is
the story? You know, presumably you know על ירך המזבח צפונה al
yerech hamizbeach tzafona presumably the north is relative to the altar. But
we'll see in a minute whether we describe north as in terms
of the north half of the Temple. So what happens when you
שחט shecht it at the top of the altar?
רבי יוסי אומר כאילו נשחטו בצפון. Rabbi Yosi omer ke'ilu nishchetu batzafon.
It's as if it's in the north, which sounds like it's not
really in the north but it's as if it's in the north.
Maybe he means my point, it's not north of the altar, but
it's as if it's in the
north. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר מחצי המזבח ולדרום כדרום מחצי המזבח
ולצפון כצפון. Rabbi Yosi berabi Yehuda omer mechatzi hamizbeach uledarom kadarom mechatzi
hamizbeach uletzafon katzafon. If it's from half to the south it's in
the south, half to the north it's in the north. So it
sounds like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosi berabi Yehuda holds like
logically you would imagine oh here's our picture right logically you would
imagine right that it's sort of centered right? I mean you know
if you're without knowing anything else you're going to assume that everything
is centered. Okay so if it's centered he seems to say fine.
It would be like a red line on the מזבח. mizbeach. Right
so it's basically it's not the it's the northern part of the
of the you know of the מקדש, mikdash, you know, or not
of the whole Temple because it has to be כנגד המזבח kineged
hamizbeach but from but from you know the north line of the
Temple onward or north of the altar includes the north half of
the altar but presumably because the north half of the altar is
in the north of the Temple. And the south half of the
altar is no good. Yes, yes, yes. That's what Mike was asking.
Okay so we're going to see what does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
think? If that's what רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosi berabi Yehuda
thinks that you know it's in the half northern half of the
מקדש mikdash you know כנגד המזבח kineged hamizbeach or on the altar
or כנגד המזבח kineged hamizbeach obviously it can't be off to the
sides, does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi hold that the whole altar is
in the north? If so why does he say it's as if
it's in the north? It's not as if, it really is in
the north. Okay so that's going to be the question. Why does
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi say you can do it on anywhere on
the top of the altar because it's as if it's in the
north? So אמר ליה רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar lei Rav
Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan. So so many, there's a רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yosi, there's a רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosi berabi Yehuda and
there's a רב אסי. Rav Assi. Okay אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן אמר היה רבי יוסי. Amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan amar
haya Rabbi Yosi.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would used to used to say כולו מזבח
בצפון קאי. kulo mizbeach batzafon kai. The entire altar is in the
north. Now presumably he's inferring this from his רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi
position that רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi position is anywhere on the top
of the altar means the entire altar's in the north so anywhere
on the top of the altar is in the north. So the
גמרא gemara says ומאי כאילו? umai ke'ilu? So what does it mean
as if? It is in the north. Okay מהו דתימא מזבח בעינן
על ירך וליכא. ma'u detema mizbeach ba'inan al yerech velaka. Like my
example with the miniature golf. You need it on the side of
the altar. On the altar itself doesn't count. It's got to be
the north side, you know, on the ground off, you know, against
the side of the altar. קא משמע לן kama'ishmalan that no you
don't need that. On the altar itself is sufficient as long as
it's taking place in the northern hemisphere
of the מקדש mikdash כנגד המזבח kineged hamizbeach or you know in
line with the altar.
So the גמרא gemara says
אמר ליה רבי זירא לרב אסי. amar lei Rabbi Zeira leRav Assi.
So Rabbi Zeira says to Rav Assi. So he said, he understood
a reasonable thing. It's sounding to me that if you infer from
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose that it's all in the north, you would
likewise infer from רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbe Yose b'Rebbe Yehuda that
it's half in the north, half in the south. That you're just
assuming that what their debate boils down to is where is the
מזבח, mizbeach, where is the altar situated? Right? That makes sense. If
you're going to infer that a position that it all works because
it's all like the north means that it's all in the north,
so the position of half and half presumably means it's half in
the north, half in the south. That's pretty
reasonable. וכי תימא הכי נמי? V'chi teima hachi nami? Yeah, that's exactly
how I'm interpreting the debate. Where is the altar situated? No, I'm
going to show you that's not true. הא והא את דאמרת משמי
דרבי יוחנן? Ha v'ha at d'amarta mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan? You yourself said
in the name of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan regarding רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rebbe Yose b'Rebbe
Yehuda, מודי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? modi Rebbe Yose b'Rebbe Yehuda? רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rebbe Yose b'Rebbe Yehuda, who says half and half,
agrees שמשחטן כנגדן בקרקע פסולה. shem'shachtan k'negdan bakarka pesula. That if you
slaughtered below it on the ground in the northern half, it's invalid.
Now, what do we mean below and on the ground? If you're
here or here, off to the east or west side, it's invalid
because it's not opposite the altar. It's not an interesting thing to
say, right? You're only, everybody agrees that when it's the north of
the altar can only be like in that space. Okay? So it's
not interesting to say on the ground. I'll just make this a
little bigger, make it a little bit
more...
Although we had another opinion said that it's broader than those lines.
It could be any point to the north of the altar, even
left and right, but if it was north of the altar. There
was an opinion that that
whole area...
You go ahead and check that your memory might be better than
mine. You go ahead and check and then get back to me.
Okay, people, go check that while I'm talking, you can get back
to me. Anyway, for now we're assuming that, for now we're assuming
that off to the east or the west is no good. It
has to be directly opposite. So saying here or here כנגד k'neged
that half space is not meaningful. So how do you get underneath
the altar? How do you get directly under it on the ground?
Right? Because there's an altar there. What do you have? You have
it hovering in the air or something? Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara
going to worry about that, okay? But for now, imagine that what
you have is, you've got somebody, like you've got a hollow in
the altar, whatever it is, somebody directly under it on the ground
space right here. So he says that that would be invalid. So,
so if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying that according to רבי
יוסי Rebbe Yose that you split it half and half, it only
works at the top of the altar. But if you are directly
below and you were on the ground, directly below the northern half,
it would be invalid. That can only make sense if you think
the altar isn't in the north. Because if the altar here were
in the north, the top north half, then if you were directly
below it on the ground, it should be okay. So that seems
to say that the position, it's not a correlation, that what they
hold about the top of the altar correlates to where they say
it's situated. Okay? Because if they, because here he holds the top
half of the altar works, but the, but the below half doesn't,
and presumably that only makes sense if it's not situated half and
half. All right, so let's take a look. Of course you could
say it is situated half and half, but the difference is this
issue of על ירך. al yerech. Right? The idea that it's not
enough to be in the northern half of the מקדש, Mikdash, you
have to be north of the altar, but the northern part of
the altar also counts. But if you're below and you're the northern
half of the מקדש Mikdash and you're not on the altar and
you're not off, off to the side of the altar, it's no
good. I could totally explain that. Air space goes up but it
doesn't go... This is north of the altar, this is the north
of the altar, but if you're directly below the north of the
altar and you're not north of the altar and you're not the
north of the altar, you're not north from the altar, you're not
north of the altar, you're just on the northern half of the
מקדש, Mikdash, it's not good. That's what, definitely what I would have
said. The גמרא Gemara does not, but does not assume that, okay?
The גמרא Gemara assumes that if it's enough to be half of
the מקדש, Mikdash, it's not really the north half of the altar,
it's really the north half of the מקדש, Mikdash, and therefore it
says, clearly, if under it doesn't work, he's not saying it's situated
half and half. So let's take a look. So אלא, ela,
so אמר ליה, amar lei, הכי קאמר רבי יוחנן. hachi ka'amar Rabbi
Yochanan. You're right, we're not inferring this from the משנה. mishna. It's
not that what they hold in the משנה mishna tells us where
the altar was situated. The debate of the משנה mishna is based
on the following verse. שניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. Shneihem mikra echad darshu.
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbe Yose b'Rebbe
Yehuda are debating the following verse. וזבחת עליו את עלותיך ואת שלמיך.
V'zavachta alav et olotecha v'et shelamiecha. You should slaughter on it your
עלותיך olotecha and your שלמיך. shelamiecha. Now, the עליו alav can be
read like עליו מטה מנשה. alav mateh Menashe. It can be read
like next to it, but we're reading it very literally as on
it. So much to the point that we're reading this literally that
תוספות, Tosafos, if you look at the first תוספות Tosafos of this
פרק, perek, תוספות Tosafos says, קדשי קדשים ששחטן בראש המזבח. kodshei kodshim
sheshachtan berosh hamizbeach.
That you slaughtered them. It sounds like בדיעבד, bedi'eved, you're not supposed
to. תוספות Tosafos says מדאורייתא שוחט לכתחילה. mid'oraisa shocheit l'chatchila. לכתחילה L'chatchila
you're allowed to שחט shecht it at the top of the altar.
כדדרשינן מזבחת עליו, kedorshinan mizvachta alav, ושמא מדרבנן. v'shema mid'rabbanan. שלא תרביץ
גללים, she-lo tarbitz glalim,
maybe rabbinically you shouldn't bring the animal to the top of the
altar because it's going to defecate, and who wants animal dung at
the top of the altar also? Seems to get a little bit
crowded and busy and having mooing cows at the top of the
altar. Okay, but what's fascinating is תוספות Tosfos thinks that the read
of the verse שחט shecht on it really means not just a
דרשה, drasha, but like really understand as a לכתחילה lichatchila you can
שחט shecht at the top of the altar. I would say פשט
pshat is, שחט shecht on the side of the altar, עליו, alav,
like עליו מטה מן השך. alav matei min hashech. Okay, but we're
reading it anyway to read that you can שחט shecht on the
top of the
altar. וזבחת עליו את עלתיך ואת שלמיך. ve-zavachta alav es oloscha v'es
shalmecha. רבי יוסי סבר כולו לעולה וכולו לשלמים. Rebbe Yosi savar kulo
l'olo v'kulo l'shlamim. You can use the whole thing for an עולה
olah and the whole thing for a שלמים shlamim if you שחט
shecht on the top of the altar. So wherever the מזבח mizbeach
is situated doesn't matter. If you're on the ground, you have to
be to the north of the altar. If you're on the top,
the whole altar is good. That's what the תורה Torah is telling
you: שחט shecht on the altar. You can use all of it
for a שלמים shlamim of course, because שלמים shlamim doesn't matter where
you are, and the same way you can use all of it
for a שלמים shlamim you can use all of it for an
עולה olah even if some of it is in the north, in
the south, even if all of it is in the
south. רבי יהודה סבר חצי לעולה וחצי לשלמים. Rebbe Yehuda savar chatzi
l'olo v'chatzi l'shlamim. The reason it says עלתיך ואת שלמיך oloscha v'es
shalmecha is to tell you you got half of it to use
for the עולה. olah. So like the מחלוקת machlokes about יום טוב,
Yom Tov, כולו להשם או כולו לכם או חצי להשם וחצי לכם,
kulo l'Hashem or kulo lachem or chatzi l'Hashem chatzi lachem, right? You
got half of it to use for the עולה, olah, the northern
half, and the half of it to use for the שלמים, shlamim,
that's the southern half. ואי סלקא דעתך כולו לעולה כשר, ve-isalkadatchach kulo
l'oloh kashar, if the point of the פסוק pasuk is to tell
you you can use the whole thing for the עולה, olah, so
השתא כולו לעולה כשר כולו לשלמים מיבעיא? hashta kulo l'olo kashar, kulo
l'shlamim mibaia? So why'd it say שלמיך, shalmecha, your שלמים? shlamim? Just
say וזבחת עליו את עלתיך. ve-zavachta alav es oloscha. Right, if you
can שחט shecht it for your עולה, olah, you can certainly שחט
shecht it for your שלמים. shlamim. So the reason it says עולה
olah and שלמים, shlamim, he says, is to tell you you split
it in half. ואידך, ve-idach, what the other one would say? איצטריך,
itzrich, you need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא עולה הוא דדחיק ליה מקום,
salkadatchach amina olah hu d'dachik lei makom, maybe the תורה Torah is
being very practical. The תורה Torah is letting you use the top
of the מזבח mizbeach because it knows there's not a lot of
space to שחט shecht an עולה. olah. You know, עולה olah you've
only got a narrow strip of the עזרה azara to שחט shecht
it. So therefore it says, you know what, if you run out
of space, use the top of the מזבח. mizbeach. And I would
have said you're not allowed to use the top of the מזבח
mizbeach for the שלמים. shlamim. We gotta designate that for backup space
for the עולה. olah. You שלמים, shlamim, you got enough space elsewhere.
Okay, אבל שלמים דלא דחיק ליה מקום, aval shlamim d'lo dachik lei
makom, but שלמים shlamim that is not pressured the space,
okay, אימא, eima, I might think no, you're not allowed to. קא
משמע לן, kamashmalan, you can use it half and half. One does
wonder for רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yosi bar Rebbe Yehuda,
what would happen if you שחט shechted a שלמים shlamim in the
northern half of the מזבח? mizbeach? Would that really be invalid? You
can שחט shecht שלמים shlamim anywhere. So presumably the half and half,
you know, so I don't know, maybe he got a designate some
space for the עולה olah for this runover. Anyway, so רבי יוחנן
Rebbe Yochanan says, I, I think the debate in the משנה Mishnah
has nothing to do with where the מזבח mizbeach is situated. It's
a debate about how to read a פסוק pasuk for this הלכה
halacha of the top of the מזבח. mizbeach. Where the מזבח mizbeach
is situated, they could say, who knows what they could say. You
could say it's all in the south and nevertheless the whole מזבח
mizbeach is good because of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, you could say
it's all whatever and it's still half and half because of the
פסוק, pasuk, who knows? Okay, so presumably now the reason we say
that according to רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, according to רבי יוסי בר
רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yosi bar Rebbe Yehuda, if you שחט shecht below
it, it's not good, is presumably and there's not, you're able to
say this, we don't know why you would say this, but now
you're able to say that for רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yosi bar Rebbe Yehuda the whole thing is in the south,
and the whole thing is in the south,
and nevertheless the פסוק pasuk is telling you that you're allowed to
use the northern half of it for the עולה. olah. And that's
why he's saying if you שחט shechted directly under, how you'll get
directly under and we'll worry in a minute, it's not good because
you're in the south of the מקדש. Mikdash. But if you're שחט
shechting at the top, ah, the top, that's a special allowance. And
at the top you have the southern half, the northern half of
the top. Okay, so we are decoupling the question of where you
can שחט shecht in the top from where exactly the מזבח mizbeach
is situated. And now actually he's making an ironic statement which is,
it could all be in the south and we could still allow
the northern half. So that's רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yosi
bar Rebbe Yehuda. Now for רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yosi, you could have
also said it's all in the south and we allow the entirety
of it because it's decoupled. So the fact that we think that
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi holds it's all in the north is not
dependent on his position in the משנה. Mishnah. Got it? In the
משנה Mishnah could be anywhere. We're there just learning from a פסוק
pasuk that you have a certain allowance to use the top of
the מזבח. mizbeach. It could be regardless of where the מזבח mizbeach
is located. So it could be that רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi in
theory could hold it's all in the south, but you're allowed to
use the entire top of the מזבח. mizbeach. So the question we're
going to have is where does רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yosi, what do
you call it? Like, now, on what basis is רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan saying that for רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi it's all in the
north since it's not dependent on his position in the משנה? Mishnah?
So let's take a
look. גופא, Gufa,
let's go back to the original statement. אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן מודה רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה שאם שחטן כנגדן בקרקע פסולה.
Amar Rav Assi amar Rebbe Yochanan, modei Rebbe Yosi bar Rebbe Yehuda
she'im shachtan k'negdan bakarka psula. If you שחט shecht below the Northern
half of the altar on the ground, it's invalid. Again, because we're
saying for רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda it's all
in the south. Okay, and therefore below it on the ground is
not good because they're in the south hemisphere. אמר ליה רב אחא
מדפתי לרבינא: Amar lei Rav Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina: מאי כנגדן בקרקע? Mai
kenegdan bakarka? How do you get below it on the ground? אי
לימא אמה יסוד אמה סובב, I leima ama yesod ama sovev,
let's say what it means is that you're on the ground in
the sense that you're standing on the סובב, sovev, on the base,
or you're standing on the walk-around. Okay, and that's what it means
you're in the space but you're on the ground. He says that's
not on the ground, that's on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. האי גופא מזבח
הוא Hai gufa Mizbe'ach hu!
That's the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So if you have an allowance for the
northern half of the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, that includes if you're not at
the top of the מזבח Mizbe'ach but if you're on the walk-around
of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. That's an allowance for being on the מזבח.
Mizbe'ach. ועוד, Ve-od, מאי כנגדן בקרקע? mai kenegdan bakarka?
So it says כנגדן בקרקע kenegdan bakarka sounds like no, you're actually
below it on the ground itself, okay? That doesn't sound like you're
on the walk-around on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. וכי תימא דעבדין מחילות, Ve-chi
teima de-avidin mechilot, so here I am trying to think about a
floating מזבח, Mizbe'ach, right? Let's say something happened, some big magnet, some
big magnet appeared in the sky, that would only work if it
were metal. Anyway, what? A floating מזבח? Mizbe'ach? Right. So anyway, so
the גמרא, Gemara, better than having a floating מזבח Mizbe'ach says, ah,
here's what you have. Let's say you dug a tunnel directly underneath.
Now that would assume that if you dig מחילות, mechilot, they have
the same קדושה kedusha of the ground of the עזרה Azara above.
Okay, because you have to be in a sanctified space, right? So
assuming it did, he's saying that would not be good because then
you would not be in the northern hemisphere, you'd still be in
the southern hemisphere. But one minute, what's that scenario?
דעבדין מחילות בקרקע ושחיט בהו De-avidin mechilot bakarka ve-shachit be-hu? וכי האי
גוונא מי הוי
מזבח? Ve-chi hai gavna mi havie Mizbe'ach? והתניא, Ve-hanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: Braisa: מזבח אדמה תעשה לי, Mizbach adama ta'aseh li, שהיה
מחובר מן האדמה, she-hei mechubar me-adama, it's connected to the ground, שלא
יבננו לא אגב מחילות, she-lo yivnennu lo agav mechilot, don't build it
on top of מחילות, mechilot, of tunnels, ולא אגב כיפין. ve-lo agav
kippin. כיפין Kippin is sort of also like
a,
what's it called, like a
domed, yeah but I mean like an underground dome, like
you know a vaulted space below, okay, a tunnel or a vaulted
space. So anyway, which is interesting in terms of that whole מדרש
Midrash you might remember about דוד המלך David HaMelech who was digging
for the basis and he hit the תהום tehom and whatever. So
exactly how to make those two fit is an interesting question. Anyway,
so we can't be talking about מחילות. mechilot.
So I don't understand, it could still be on the אדמה, adama,
you just go tunnel like 10 feet below it. There's still plenty
of ground between.
No, but obviously it's not floating in air. The whole point about
this of אדמה adama means it has to be all compressed dirt
below it, there can't be a cavity. Now how far below? If
you have a thousand feet below, maybe, I don't know exactly how
far that goes. Okay.
But I still
don't see what
you get from that, meaning אדמה adama means you can't make it
out of, you know.
I understand, they're not reading it just the material you make it,
they're reading it as it connected to the אדמה. adama. Okay, I
don't know what to tell you, that's the way they're reading it,
okay. And you're right, you could have said connected to the אדמה
adama doesn't mean that 20 feet down there can't be some vaulted
space. But that's how they're reading it, it's a fascinating read. Again,
I, and if that goes, like Michael, you know, you get worked
up about how do you get this from the פסוק, pasuk, you
know, I just give them, they drew their דרשות drashos the way
they did them. But what I want to know is how does
this fit in with other statements, right? Like how does this fit
in with the whole, you know, מדרש Midrash in סוכה Sukkah which
sounds like דווקא davka there were some cavities underneath and so forth.
But you know what it reminds me of? Yeah? That מעשה maaseh
with אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi on הר הכרמל Har HaKarmel when they,
they started doing מחילות mechilot under there. Oh that's interesting. Was that
to prevent you from doing that?
Wasn't that to make it all filled with water to make it
a bigger נס nes or something?
No, he did that later, but like they started doing it, they
started tunneling under there, you know.
Okay, anyway, לא צריכא, lo tzricha, so here's the scenario: דבצרי בצורי.
de-batzrei bitzurei.
So, so they cut, they shrunk it. What does that mean? What
it means is no, you're not going to have it in the
way the מזבח Mizbe'ach is configured. What it means is if for
some reason they had to reconfigure the מזבח Mizbe'ach and they actually,
you know,
cut its space in half.
Were they allowed to do that?
Apparently, I mean, you know the idea 32, 30, 28, that was
the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai in terms of the size.
But those are fixed dimensions though, doesn't it?
No, not of the, no. The dimensions of the תורה Torah are
not the dimensions that they used in the מקדש. Mikdash. So if
for whatever reason they needed to reconfigure the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, okay, and
make it smaller, and that opened up the space below the northern
half, that would be no good. Okay, now if you read it
that way then it's clearly a statement that it's in the south.
Because if they really reconfigured it and you're in the northern what
used to be the northern half, you're north of the current מזבח.
Mizbe'ach. The current מזבח Mizbe'ach is now half where it was and
you're north of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So if that's what he means,
then clearly he means that he believes the whole מזבח Mizbe'ach is
in the south. Okay, so now we have רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda who says half and half, we're saying he
means the whole מזבח Mizbe'ach is in the south. And nevertheless based
on a verse permitting the northern half of the מזבח Mizbeach if
you're on the מזבח. Mizbeach. And רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose who says
you can use the whole מזבח, Mizbeach, in theory he could also
say the מזבח Mizbeach is in the south and it's a special
permission, but we're saying he says the whole מזבח Mizbeach is in
the north. So you got one of them saying the whole מזבח
Mizbeach is in the north and one saying the whole מזבח Mizbeach
is in the south. So now we're going to get into that.
Okay. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rebbe Zeira, said רבי זירא, Rebbe Zeira,
אפשר איתא להא דרבי יוחנן, Efshar isa le-ha de-Rebbe Yochanan, is it
possible this happens sometimes like רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said this assertion
about רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose that it's all in the north. Where
did he get that from? He's just asserting it at this stage
because we're not saying it's dependent on his position in the משנה.
Mishna. So is it possible that this idea, this tradition, it must
have been a tradition he had that רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose says
it's all in the north. But you know, is it possible this
tradition existed and there's no hint for it somewhere in some Tannaitic
literature? Like you know, I love that attitude, like there's got to
be, all truth is in the תורה. Torah. And if this tradition
is true then there's got to be somewhere we can find this
in the משנה. Mishna. אפשר איתא להא דרבי יוחנן, Efshar isa le-ha
de-Rebbe Yochanan, is it possible this statement of רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan
that for רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose it's all in the north, is
it possible that's actually true ולא תנינא לה במתניתין ve-lo tanina lei
be-matnitin and it won't doesn't exist anywhere in a משנה Mishna or
in a ברייתא? Braita? נפק דק ואשכח דתנן, Nafaq daq ve-ashkah de-tenan,
he found that we taught the following משנה Mishna in תמיד. Tamid.
Okay. ביררו משם עצי תאנה יפים לסדר המערכה. Bereru misham atzei te’ena
yafim le-seder ha-ma’aracha.
So this is talking about how they would select wood to put
on the, you know, on the fire
on top of the altar. So it says it was, you know,
they took out from there, from you know, the chamber where they
would have the wood, good fig wood לסדר
המערכה
השניה של קטורת.
le-seder ha-ma’aracha
ha-shniya shel ktoret.
They were selecting the wood to use for the second מערכה, ma’aracha,
not fire, what do you call that, where you have the logs,
pyre?
Yeah, pyre sounds like also that a fire is already burning. Isn't
there a wood for like, a wood pile? I don't know, isn't
there something for the arrangement of the wood? Anyway, whatever. Okay anyway,
we'll call it a pyre.
Anyway so they arranged the second fire.
Anyway, okay, pyre fire, anyway so they arranged it, okay? So now
they're selecting wood to add to the second, you know, pyre, the
second, you know, fire on the top of the altar. The one
that they're going to not burn the entrails on, they would have
a second fire where they would select from the coals to use
for burning the קטורת. ktoret. Okay, and for what?
Yeah, the one that the קרבנות korbanot
was like right in the middle. The קרבנות korbanot one is in
the middle,
a big one here, the main קרבנות korbanot one is in the
middle, that's your fire, and there's going to be another one that's
going to be right here, okay? And that's going to be which
we're going to see in a minute, which is going to be
in the southwest corner and they're going to use from that coals
in order for burning the קטורת ktoret on the inner golden altar.
Right? רש״י Rashi says that it might, we'll see why. רש״י Rashi
says the reason it might be this פשט pshat of why it's
fig wood is just that that's good wood, maybe it's aromatic wood.
But רש״י Rashi also says that it's nice because like, you know,
it was connected to saving אדם Adam from, you know, covering up
his חטא chet afterwards, the nakedness. Anyway, יפים לסדר המערכה השניה של
קטורת, Yafim le-seder ha-ma’aracha ha-shniya shel ktoret, they got nice wood for
the second pyre של קטורת shel ktoret that they were going to
use for the burning of the incense. כנגד קרן מערבית דרומית, Keneged
keren maaravit dromit, in the southwest corner. משוך מן הקרן כלפי צפון
ארבע אמות, Mashuch min ha-keren klapei tzafon arba amot, four אמות amot
sort of north from the very edge. Alright? So here we'll draw
a right a
big picture.
There you got it. And I do need more colors.
Okay, okay,
so
anyway, here it would be, okay? So here would be the second
one and it would be, this is right, north, east, south, west,
it
would be in the southwest corner but it would be four אמות.
amot.
Thank you. It'll be four אמות amot away from the southernmost southernmost
edge. We'll see why in a minute. Okay. משוך מן הקרן כלפי
צפון ארבע אמות, Mashuch min ha-keren klapei tzafon arba amot, so four
אמות amot to the north, four אמות amot removed from the southernmost
edge. באומד חמש סאין גחלים, Be-omed chamesh se’in gechalim, approximately five סאין
se’in of coals, one minute, to produce approximately five סאין se’in of
coals so that when you dig in for the coals there's a
nice pile there. Okay, ובשבת באומד שמונה סאין גחלים, u-be-shabbat be-omed shmona
se’in gechalim, by שבת Shabbat you would try to have as much
to produce eight סאין se’in of coals because you would need also
not just for the burning of the incense but on שבת Shabbat
you would also you would take from it and you would bring
it into the golden altar and put the coals on the golden
altar to burn the incense. You'd do that twice a day during
every day including שבת. Shabbat. And on שבת Shabbat you would take
from the two little spoons that they had on the שולחן Shulchan
that had in them frankincense and you would put them on the
outer on the altar. So you understand? You would take from the
coals and bring it to the inner altar to burn the incense
in the inner altar twice a day. And on שבת Shabbat you
would take from the שולחן, Shulchan,
can use this, here,
there's your מנורה, Menorah, whatever, okay,
there's your שולחן, Shulchan,
there's
your altar.
So what you would do is, right, you would take from this
twice,
morning
and evening, to go ahead and to burn on the altar, right,
and you would also you take from and on שבת Shabbat you
would take from the you would I'm sorry, whoops, from the שולחן,
shulchan, I knew there was a reason I drew the שולחן. shulchan.
And on שבת Shabbat you would take from the שולחן shulchan once,
and you would take the actual frankincense that was at the base
on the on the you know, on the table part of the
שולחן, shulchan, not on the not on the heightened shelves, you would
take from the base from the table and you would burn from
the frankincense on the שולחן shulchan on that altar.
Okay, so why how do we get five whatever,
that's just the amount they figured because you want to shovel it
in and get a certain amount and whatever, so in order to
be a good so, רש"י, Rashi, you look at רש"י. Rashi.
But what about the four אמות?
amot? I mean, to me we're getting there. That's we're gonna have
to finish quoting the משנה. mishnah. You can work think about your
theories, we've gotta finish quoting the משנה mishnah first. Okay, ששם היו
נותנים שני בזיכי לבונה של לחם הפנים. she-sham hayu notnim shenei bezikhei
levonah shel lechem hapanim.
That's where they would do the two scoops of frankincense of לחם
הפנים. lechem hapanim. ומה סימנה? u-mah simanah? רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose היא,
hi, and what's your indication that this is רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose?
Now how this is even relevant to what this proves about where
the מזבח mizbeach is we have no idea yet. The key is
gonna be, as Michael correctly noted, the fact that you have to
move the fire four אמות. amot. What is that telling us? So
that's gonna be the focal point. But first how do we know
to link this to רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose? דתניא, de-tanya, we taught
in a
בריתא, beraita, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, זה סימן. zeh siman.
So that's why it said מה סימנה. mah simanah. Okay, this is
how you know exactly where this we're gonna read this, like, where
this fire was. כל הניטל בפנים לנתן בחוץ, kol ha-nital bifnim lenatan
bachutz, anything that is taken from the inside, from the from the
היכל, heichal, to put on the in the עזרה, azarah, אינו ניטל
אלא בסמוך. eino nital ela besamuch. You have to put it near
where you exit the door of the היכל. heichal. שאין לפנים, she-ein
lifnim, that there's nothing from the inside that goes on the outside,
it's funny, those two words are a little funny, anyway, that gets
put elsewhere. וכל הניטל בחוץ נתן בפנים, ve-kol ha-nital bachutz natan bifnim,
and anything that's taken from the outside and going to be put
on inside in the היכל, heichal, אינו ניטל אלא בסמוך, eino nital
ela besamuch,
similarly, you're only going to take it from the place nearest to
the היכל. heichal. שאין לפנים, she-ein lifnim,
that nothing sort of else is going to be done on the
inside that's not taken from a place right nearby. Now what does
this mean? כל הניטל בפנים לנתן בחוץ מאי ניהו? kol ha-nital bifnim
lenatan bachutz mai nihu? What does it mean, stuff you take on
the inside to put on the out has to be done immediately
when you exit? So the more normal thing to think about, unless
we were already thinking about the frankincense, the more natural thing to
think about would have been the spilling of the blood, which is
what we had talked about before. You come out, you spill the
blood at the base and you spill it at the at the
western base, which is the first base that you hit, which makes
sense. Anything you're going from outside to in and in to out,
you do at the nearby part of the altar. Okay, so מאי
ניהו, mai nihu, אילימא שיריים, ileima shirayim, so if it's the blood,
בהדיא כתיב בהו, behedya ketiv behu, okay, the הלכה halachah is true
but it's so obvious that I don't need רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
to tell me that. Don't give me a סימן, siman, it's a
פסוק. pasuk. אל יסוד מזבח העולה אשר פתח אהל מועד, el yesod
mizbeach ha-olah asher petach ohel moed,
it says explicitly, pour it by the base that's by the opening,
so I don't need רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's nice little סימן. siman.
Of course, you know, what do we say on פסח? Pesach?
Who is it that gives them סימנים? simanim? רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose?
Was that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose also?
Was it? Was it?
No, no, רבי יהודה היה נותן בהם סימנים, Rabbi Yehuda hayah noten
bahem simanim, right, דצ"ך עד"ש באח"ב. detzach adash beachav. Alright,
it's a פסוק, pasuk, fine, it's a פסוק, pasuk, but I gotta
tell you, it's a lot easier to remember the מכות makkos if
you know דצ"ך עד"ש באח"ב. detzach adash beachav. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, number one, he wouldn't be giving a סימן, siman, it's
a פסוק. pasuk. Number two, וטו, ve-tu, כל הניטל בחוץ נתן בפנים
מאי ניהו? kol ha-nital bachutz natan bifnim mai nihu?
When it says stuff on the outside gets put on the inside
and you take it by nearby, the stuff that's right near the
inside, what is it from the outside that goes on the inside?
There's no blood you take on the outside to put on I
mean, you know, off of the altar on the outside to put
on the altar on the inside. אילימא גחלים ileima gechalim של יום
הכפורים, shel Yom HaKippurim,
now maybe it's the coals of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So now
clearly we gotta move away from blood. If there's something you take
on the outer altar to bring to the inside, it's gotta be
coals. Okay, so what coals? So if it's the coals of יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, בהדיא כתיב בהו, behedya ketiv behu, again that's an
explicit פסוק, pasuk, ולקח מלא המחתה גחלי אש מעל המזבח מלפני ה'.
velakach melo hamachtah gachalei esh meal hamizbeach milifnei Hashem.
So it says explicitly from in front of God, and in front
of God means by the opening of the היכל. heichal. Okay, so
therefore, right, so therefore
yes, those are true. The blood you put right at the base
as soon as you come out. The coals for יום כיפור Yom
Kippur you take and they're right at the western part of the
altar right near the היכל, heichal, but you get that from a
מפורש meforash פסוק. pasuk.
But it's still a little bit down though, based
on we'll get to where it's down or not. But okay, so
אלא, ela, so but we're on the right track now. It's gotta
be about coals and about incense, but it's gotta be something that's
not explicit in the פסוקים. pesukim. אלא כל הניטל בפנים לנתן בחוץ,
ela kol ha-nital bifnim lenatan bachutz, שני בזיכי לבונה של לחם הפנים.
shenei bezikhei levonah shel lechem hapanim. So what is the stuff on
the inside you're putting on the outside? It is the two scoops
of frankincense of the bread
which is
done on שבת. Shabbat. but that's what we're talking about here. That's
not explicit in the verse. Okay.
And
and never says you put it on the מזבח? mizbeach?
No, never says that you put it, where you put it on
the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay. So the fact that
actually it might also not say explicitly that you put it on
the מזבח. mizbeach.
Maybe
you don't know that it's בסמוך? besamuch?
No, I mean maybe it would be the מזבח הזהב. mizbeach hazahav.
I
have to check the פסוקים psukim actually. What does it say there
by the by the שולחן? shulchan?
I don't know, you could check the פסוקים, psukim, I'm not remembering
offhand if it even says that you put it on the outer
altar, but certainly it doesn't say where on the outer altar.
על המזבח אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח.
Al hamizbeach
esh tamid tukad al hamizbeach. No,
no, that's by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Where does it say that
you burn the the לבונה levonah of the שולחן shulchan on the
מזבח? mizbeach? Michael can check for us. Okay, so anyway, so it
might say outer altar, though I'm not sure it does, but even
if it does say, I mean it does say לא תעלה עליו
lo ta'aleh alav by the inner altar קטורת זרה ועולה ומנחה. ktoret
zara v'ola u'mincha. But what's קטורת זרה? ktoret zara? Anyway, you can
check, but certainly it doesn't say where on the outer altar. So
the idea that it is on a sort of the western corner,
now why the southwest we'll get to, okay? But the idea that
it's on the western corner, the place that you hit when you
leave, that's learned from the spilling of blood. The same way you
spill the blood on the western base, you burn you burn the
incense from the שולחן shulchan on the on a fire that is
at the western side of the altar that's as juxtaposed to exiting
the היכל Heichal as possible. Okay, clear? Yes.
So I mean it is but it isn't, you know, but was
really just supposed to exiting the היכל Heichal as possible you'd put
it on the north part of that, northwest.
No, if you if you come out here in the center then
and then if you think about it this is the southwestern, it's
the place that is closest because it's in the west, it's the
closest to where I left. You gotta go up the altar to
do it. So you come out of the altar you gotta go
up. So once I'm going up to the altar which I'm coming
up from the south side, the west is the closest to where
I left the היכל, Heichal, and the south is the shortest distance
to get there.
Right, and south is the closest to where you're starting.
Northwest is no closer. All of west is assuming the מזבח, mizbeach,
assuming the מזבח mizbeach is in the center, just one minute, assuming
the מזבח mizbeach is in the center,
then the entire west is all equally close. Okay, I mean we'll
get to it in a minute. Anyway, the southwest is certainly better
than the northwest, it's shorter distance. We'll get to this in a
minute.
They have the north part of the altar.
Yeah, well we're going to get to that, we'll get to that
diagram in a minute. Okay. So, okay, anyway, so so you know
you burn the frankincense in the western part from the fact that
you spill the blood on the western base. And again presumably it's
the southwest because that's the first part you hit. So that's in
burning the incense. שיריים. Shirayim. הנינתן בחוץ. Hanitan bachutz.
Now הנינתן בחוץ ינתנו בפנים, Hanitan bachutz yinatnu bifnim, what's the stuff
you take from the top that you put on the inside? So
that's גחלים דכל יומא ויומא, gechalim d'chol yoma v'yoma, that is the
coals that you're going to use for burning the daily incense, okay?
דגמרינן מגחלים שיום הכיפורים, D'gamrinan migechalim sheYom Hakipurim,
we learn from יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. By יום כיפור Yom Kippur
it explicitly says you take the coals מלפני ה', milifnei Hashem, which
means as close to the היכל Heichal as possible, from the west.
It doesn't say that by the daily burning of the קטורת. ktoret.
So you're going to learn. So yes, it is true. What we
do have explicit is spilling the blood and the coals of יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. And both of those happen right at this sort
of west edge of the altar. From there we're going to learn
that the burning of the לבונה levonah from the לחם הפנים Lechem
Hapanim and the taking of the coals inside for the daily קטורת
ktoret also happens at the west edge from a fire that's at
the west edge of the altar. Now, now we gotta get to
the ארבע אמות arba amot off the south, okay? And this is
going to be why it's relevant. So that allows us to say
that this משנה Mishna that says ארבע אמות arba amot off the
south is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi because here רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
makes it clear that the fire you would use for the incense
in both directions would be at the west. So this משנה Mishna
that says it's at the southwest is רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Now
of course the question would be, couldn't it be like maybe everybody
agrees to that? רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi just gave a סימן. siman.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to question that later. But
for now we clearly have רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi associated with making
a statement that the fire is in the west and therefore we're
going to assign the authorship and say the משנה Mishna that says
this ארבע אמות arba amot away from the southwest corner we're going
to say that's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Okay, and now we're going
to prove that that shows that the whole מזבח mizbeach is in
the north. Let's see how we're going to prove that.
Okay. ומאי קסבר? U'mai kasavar? Now what does he hold about where
this altar is situated? אי קסבר כוליה מזבח בדרום קאי, Ei kasavar
kulei mizbeach b'darom kai, if he holds the whole altar is in
the south, so עשרים ושבע אמה איכא. esrim v'sheva ama ika. So
now here's the assumption. The assumption is
it needs to be something that's... it's gotta be not just near
in the sense of in the west, it's also gotta be מלפני
ה', milifnei Hashem, it's gotta be in front of the door. Okay,
so here's what you've got. Okay, you've got your altar...
Okay, it's thirty-two at the base, it's like twenty-eight at the top.
Okay, that's your altar. Okay, and you've got your fire here.
מערכה
שנייה. ma'aracha shniya.
Your מערכה שנייה ma'aracha shniya here. Okay, now you've got here
your holy מקדש, Mikdash, alright, and you've
got your עזרה azara here and whatever your היכל, heichal, your אולם.
ulam. Okay, and you've got your door right here. Okay, now this
door actually this door was wider.
This door was twenty
and this door was ten. And this is clearly situated the door
to the אולם ulam and to the היכל heichal are clearly situated
in the center. Okay, so if the whole thing, so what we
have to assume is we have to assume that the fire has
to be opposite the door, presumably the door of the היכל. heichal.
Alright? Now, if this whole thing is situated in the oh the
first we're saying it's all in the דרום, darom, it's all in
the south. So if it's all in the south, okay, and we're
taking for granted that it's
easier to move the מקדש Mikdash than the מזבח, mizbe'ach, right?
Exactly. We're taking for granted, we're taking for granted again like I
said that the door of the היכל heichal and of the אולם
ulam are exactly in the center. That's taken for granted. So if
the whole thing, I got the wrong one here,
so if the whole thing and weren't there like side doors too?
Yes, but please we're not going to worry about that. Okay, so
if the whole thing is in the south, okay, so that means
that the door of the היכל heichal is, if this is the
line of the south and the היכל heichal is exactly half and
half, I mean if this is the midline, okay, then the door
of the היכל heichal is only five אמות amot here and five
אמות amot here.
You got that?
Okay, yes, everybody gets that point. Okay, so this has to be
opposite the what do you call it had this has to be
opposite the door of the היכל. heichal. So it can't be down
here, it's got to be like way up here, it's got to
be at this corner. Alright Michael, it's got to be way up
here at this corner. Okay, now since here
this goes in an אמה ama here and an אמה ama here
whatever, an אמה ama for the יסוד yesod and an אמה ama
for the סובב, sovev, whatever, anyway, but or whatever, anyway, so here
how far in would this have to be in order to be
within this space without so let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says so ומאי קסבר קסבר כולי מזבח בדרום קאי עשרים ושבע
בעי למיתי. u'mai kasvar kasvar kulei mizbe'ach b'darom ka'i esrim u'shva ba'ei
lemiti. It would have to be twenty-seven אמות amot in from the
the first of all you wouldn't describe it as the southwest, you'd
describe it as the northwest. But if we're going to start with
the southwest, it would have to be twenty-seven אמות amot in. Why
would it have to be twenty-seven אמות amot in? What would have
to be twenty-seven אמות? amot? The fire, twenty-seven אמות amot in from
from the south. Why would it have to be twenty-seven אמות? amot?
Because it's going to assume that we're going to start counting from
the base, okay, from the base of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So from
the base here is thirty-two. This is the easy way to do
it. From the base to the edge is thirty-two. You can get
it, you don't have to get it to the very edge, you
have five אמות amot because again if it's if it's all in
the south then there's five אמות amot of the door of the
opening that's that's within the south. So you don't have to get
it all thirty-two, you only have to get it twenty-seven. Okay, but
it would still have to be twenty-seven removed from the southern edge.
Okay, anyway, you would describe it as the northwest, you wouldn't describe
it as the southwest. Okay, ואיכא דאמרי כולי מזבח בדרום קאי עשרים
ושבע בעי למיתי ואי נמי קסבר קדושת היכל ואולם חדא היא עשרים
ותרתי בעי למיתי. u'ika d'amri kulei mizbe'ach b'darom ka'i esrim u'shva ba'ei
lemiti v'ee nami kasvar kedushat heichal v'ulam chada hi esrim v'tarti ba'ei
lemiti. Now maybe you don't need to get in by the opening
of the היכל heichal door. Maybe you can get it by the
opening of the אולם ulam door which is bigger and that was
twenty. So that would give you ten אמות amot of a door
to the south. Fine, but from down here you go thirty-two minus
ten, you'd still have to move it twenty-two from the south corner
to get it by that door. So if that's true, so where
were we? עשרים ותרתי בעי למיתי. esrim v'tarti ba'ei lemiti. You'd have
to move it twenty-two from the edge. ואי קסבר חציו בצפון וחציו
בדרום חדסרי בעי למיתי. v'ee kasvar chetzyo b'tzafon v'chetzyo b'darom chad-asrei ba'ei
lemiti. Now if it was middle, okay, I got to move the
whole thing again. Okay,
but if the line goes down the middle here,
okay, so the door here is five and five, but it's now
down the middle. The middle here is sixteen, right? The מזבח mizbe'ach
is sixteen down the middle and five of the door is you
know is now in the southern in the southern hemisphere. So that
means eleven from the edge will get you to the space of
the door. But you would still need to move it eleven from
the edge. ואי קסבר חציו בצפון וחציו בדרום
חדסרי בעי למיתי.
v'ee kasvar chetzyo
b'tzafon v'chetzyo b'darom chad-asrei ba'ei lemiti.
You'd have to move it eleven from the edge. ואלא קסבר קדושת
היכל ואולם חדא היא. v'ela kasvar kedushat heichal v'ulam chada hi. Fine,
maybe you don't have to get the the היכל heichal door, maybe
the אולם ulam door which gets you a door of twenty, there's
ten in the southern hemisphere. Fine, but the whole מזבח mizbe'ach is
sixteen in the southern hemisphere. So you'd have to get six off
the the edge to get into the space of the door. Okay,
so השתא היא, hashta hi, ששה באמתא, shisha b'amasei,
you'd have to still move it six off the southern corner. ואלא
לאו משום דקסבר כלו מזבח בצפון קאי. Ve'ela lav mishum degasavar kulo
mizbe'ach batzafon kai.
It's all in the north. Now if it's all in the north,
what's the idea for ארבע אמות? arba amos? Okay, והני, ve'hani, let's
take a look. ארבע אמות: arba amos: אמת יסוד, amas yesod, ואמת
סובב, ve'amas sovev, ואמת מקום קרנות, ve'amas mekom kranos, ואמת מקום רגלי
הכהנים. ve'amas mekom raglei hakohanim.
Okay, so here rather than saying until now we've been saying how
much you have to move it off the side, the minimum you
have to move it in order to get it in front of
the door. Okay? But if the whole thing is in the north,
it's the opposite problem. If the whole thing is in the north,
right, then you have to keep it as close to the southern
edge as possible because you only have five אמות amos of the
door in the north. The whole thing is in the north, so
you can't move it more than five אמות. amos. Now if you
start counting, though, before you get to the top, before you have
any open space to put it, you have one אמה amah of
the base,
right? One אמה amah of the walk around, right? Because you had
the other sort of thing here. So now you're two אמות amos
in. You get to the corner, right, you're three אמות amos in.
Okay. And then in addition to the corners, because you can't just
have the כהנים kohanim walking between the corners because then how do
they get around it? There was another אמה amah in that the
כהנים kohanim would use as space to walk around, like a sidewalk
or whatever. Anyway, so before you have any place to put the
fire, you're four אמות amos off of the base. So you only
have that exact space between four אמות amos and five אמות amos
to put the fire. Anything more, right, you're going to be too
far. So when it says you remove it four אמות, amos, it
means no more than five אמות. amos. You've got to actually put
it, if you think about the open space, he's saying you have
to put it at the immediate first open space that you have.
Okay,
excellent. Okay, so you gotta put it at the immediate first, at
the immediate first,
you got it? So really it's a funny way of saying it,
though, because what he's really, rather than saying you put it four
אמות amos
drawn in off of the, you know, drawn in from the southern
base, what you're really saying is that's if you're measuring it from
the ground. But a normal person would measure it from the top
because that's where you're putting it. And what you're really saying is
you put it at the immediate first
southernmost corner that you can at the top. Okay, but that's how
we're reading it. והני ארבע אמות: אמת יסוד ואמת סובב ואמת מקום
קרנות ואמת מקום רגלי הכהנים, דכי מסקו לקמי טפי, Ve'hani arba amos:
amas yesod ve'amas sovev ve'amas mekom kranos ve'amas mekom raglei hakohanim, dechi
masku lekamei tavei,
if you were to move it anything more than four אמות amos
off the base, meaning anything more from the first
southernmost corner that you could put it in, southwestern corner, תו ליכא
פתח, tu leka pesach, it would no longer be because the פתח
pesach exists between, ends at five אמות. amos. All right, so that
now, so because it says ארבע אמות arba amos and the ארבע
אמות arba amos measure only makes sense if it's all in the
north, and then ארבע אמות arba amos means ארבע אמות arba amos
from the base, and it's a minimum, not a maximum—or I mean
whatever, it's a maximum, not a minimum—okay, now we understand it, and
now we've assigned this to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, and that tells
us for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose it's all in the north. Okay,
but now the גמרא's Gemara gonna say wait, there's other ways of
reading this ארבע אמות. arba amos. אמר אדא בר אהבה, הא מני
רבי יהודה היא. Amar Ada bar Ahava, ha mani Rabbi Yehuda hi.
No, no, no. He says I think it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
דתניא, Detanya, רבי יהודה אומר: מזבח ממוצע ועומד באמצע עזרה, ושלשים ושתים
אמה היו לו. Rabbi Yehuda omer: Mizbe'ach memutza ve'omed be'emtzah azara, u'sheloshim
u'shtayim amah hayu lo.
It's exactly in the middle, half in the north, half in the
south, and I'm going to get this ארבע אמות arba amos of
the fire to work for position of exactly in the middle. How?
עשר אמה כנגד פתחו של היכל, אחת עשרה אמה מכאן ואחת עשרה
אמה מכאן. Asser amah keneged pitcho shel Heichal, achat esrei amah mikan
ve'achat esrei amah mikan.
So there is, it's exactly in the middle.
Okay, you've got the opening of the
היכל, Heichal, right, which takes up ten אמות amos of the thirty-two.
Okay, so total here is ten, right? That's ten. So now you
have twenty-two left. So after the opening of the היכל, Heichal, you
got eleven אמות amos here and eleven אמות amos here. Okay,
where are we? נמצא מזבח מכוון
כנגד היכל. Nimtzah mizbe'ach mechuvam keneged Heichal.
It's exactly opposite the היכל. Heichal. Now there's something that's not clear
from these words. You would just think it means this is dead
center and this is dead center. רש"י Rashi actually says it means
more because רש"י Rashi says that the actual inner space of the
היכל Heichal was twenty אמות. amos. Okay, the inner space of the
היכל Heichal was ten here and then five and five, twenty אמות.
amos. But the thickness of the walls was six אמות. amos.
Okay, six אמות amos thick walls, five space till you get to
the door, ten to the door, five and then six is thirty-two.
Anyway, the inner space here is twenty and the thickness of the
walls is six.
I thought the היכל Heichal was wider than the מזבח? Mizbe'ach?
No. So the היכל Heichal is exactly—the אולם. Ulam. Okay, the אולם
Ulam goes out, but the היכל Heichal is exactly the same width
of the מזבח. Mizbeach. So that's what he's saying, the whole structure
of the היכל Heichal is exactly the same width and they're both
dead center. All right?
Perfectly symmetrical. All right. נמצא—whoa Nimtza whoa
whoa—now how is this going to fit with the idea that the
fire is four אמות amot removed? So let's take a look. נמצא
מזבח מכוון כנגד היכל. Nimtza Mizbeach mechhuvan kineged Heichal. סוף סוף Sof
sof לפי יהודה lephi Yehuda חד סרי בעי למיסיה. chad sari baei
lemeisaya.
You have to remove it. The fire, if it's exactly here, okay,
mid, then you need to get it from down here, you need
to get eleven, right? Now you could even just look at it
in terms of the dimension of the היכל. Heichal. You gotta get
it eleven to get to where the door is. All right. וכי
תימא, Vechi teima,
and if you say, ואי קסבר קדושת היכל ואולם חד מילתא היא,
ve’i kasavar kedushat Heichal ve’Ulam chad milta hi, it's enough to get
it in front of the—it's all one considered unit and it's enough
to get it in front of the door of the אולם, Ulam,
שית בעי למיסיה. shit baei lemeisaya. So fine. So the door of
the אולם Ulam was actually—actually it just strikes me interesting,
no, but I guess I realize now, but I just realized now
also that the door of the אולם Ulam was exactly מכוון mechhuvan
כנגד kineged
the interior of the היכל. Heichal. You know what I mean? It's
just the thickness... that was interesting, I didn't realize that. Anyway, so
if you've got now—if it's enough to be by the door of
the אולם, Ulam, then it should be enough to get six. Why
does he say four? I mean, right? Not enough. You should need
six. Four wouldn't suffice. Okay.
I guess it depends if you're going from the bottom up or...
That is the obvious answer. Yes. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא
שית בעי למיסיה. ha shit baei lemeisaya. So the גמרא Gemara says
like Michael said, I never would have thought when it says you
remove the fire X אמה amah that we're measuring from the base.
You're measuring from where you could put the fire. You measure from
the top. This is a much better read if you ask me.
So it says, no, מי קסברת, mi kasavrat, what makes you think,
הני ארבע אמות בהדי אמה יסוד ואמה סובב? hani arba amot bahadi
amah yesod ve’amah sovev?
Who says we're measuring from the base? No, ארבע אמות בר ממה
יסוד ואמה סובב. arba amot bar mimmah yesod ve’amah sovev.
We're counting it from—we're counting it from the top. So the top
is two אמות amot inserted. We're—okay, fine. Once you get to the
top, okay, there might be walk-around or whatever, but this is the
top. So if you want to say this is of course logically
how you would measure, here you are, you got to the top
of the altar, okay, doesn't really matter what's at the base, where
do I put the fire? You put the fire in the southwestern
corner four אמות amot from the edge, meaning four אמות amot from
where the edge of the top space is, okay, which is exactly
six אמות—right, amot which is six אמות amot from the base—which exactly
gets you the minimum to be in front of the door of
the אולם. Ulam. So that's the minimum you need, four אמות amot
from the surface of the top of the altar gets you in
front of the door of the אולם, Ulam, and anywhere there for
the next twenty אמות amot will be okay, okay? But you're supposed
to do it presumably in the south because that's the first place
you hit. That's a much better read. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, ונוקמה כרבי יוסי בממוצע. venokmah keRabbi Yosi bimmu tza. So
now, okay, so now here's the question though. You're right, that's a
very nice read and it makes sense if it's halfway down the
middle. So what forced רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to say that for
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi it was all in the north? We've just
have now a lovely read of this to say that it's smack
in the middle. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר—wait wait no, let me make sure I just read that question
right.
This note says רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi? didn't really say where it
was.
Well, he didn't, right, that's what I said, that we said that
he didn't say it. We're trying to infer it from this. Right.
So the גמרא—right—so Gemara a
minute. Oh, oh, no, this is the question. Why
you, רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Adda bar Ahava, that said it's
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's smack
in the middle and therefore I can make this whole thing work
with a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position that it's smack in the
middle? So, okay, you're right. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda explicitly says it's
in the middle and you made it work beautifully. So why did
you just say it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda smack in the middle?
Why not actually just challenge the assertion of רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosi
Say, hey, you're claiming רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says it's all in
the north, I can tell you רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi holds it's
half and half, okay? You got it? The argument was, oh, this
only works for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, and it's all in the
north and this is what the four אמות amot means. He says,
no, it works for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's half and half.
Okay. Say, and then why not just say, and it works for
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi and maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi holds it's
half and half? ומאי טעמא—so Umai ta’ama where where—okay, ונוקמה כרבי יוסי
בממוצע. venokmah keRabbi Yosi bimmu tza.
Why not claim that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi himself holds half and
half? Why do you go running to רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? We
can now say that רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi holds half and half.
So the answer is משום דרבי יהודה. mishum deRabbi Yehuda. משום דרבי
יהודה שמענא ליה מממוצע בהדיא, mishum d'Rebbe Yehuda shamana lay mimutza behedya,
because רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda explicitly said it's half and half. But
now once you've made this assertion, it's true. There's no proof that
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi says it's all in the north. You could
read רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi. just like we read רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda to say it's half and half. רב שרביא אמר Rav Sharvaya
amar הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי. ha mani Rebbe Yosi HaGlili. This
is a different רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yosi, Now we got a רבי
יוסי, Rebbe Yosi a רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, a רבי יוסי in
סתם רבי יוסי stam Rebbe Yosi which is רבי יוסי בר חלפתא
Rebbe Yosi bar Chalafta and now we have רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rebbe
Yosi HaGlili.
This is רבי יוסי הגלילי.
Rebbe
Yosi HaGlili.
That's the second day in the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. Exactly, you
can go with the youngest, yes, correct.
Okay, דתניא detanya רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר Rebbe Yosi HaGlili omer מתוך
שנאמר ונתת כיור בין אהל מועד ובין המזבח. mitoch shenemar venatata kiyor
bein ohel moed uvein hamizbe'ach.
This idea, okay, that כולו מזבח kulo mizbe'ach is, what do you
call it, is בצפון, betzafon, okay, is רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rebbe Yosi
HaGlili. Okay, so how are we going to see this? Because and
now we're going to get it from where the כיור kiyor is
placed. You know, let's just stop here for today and we will
pick
up with this tomorrow.